We know we need to increase the strength
of the left ventricle as a starting place.
If we do that, that will
allow or actually produce
and result in an increase
in stroke volume.
So, what does that mean for training?
Well, fundamentally,
outside of things like exercise technique
and timing and nutrition
and all that other stuff,
if we're just talking about
the background physiology,
we have two avenues or areas to push on
to improve our VO2 max.
We have our stroke volume
and our a-vO2 difference.
So, there's a lot of ways
we go about improving both of them.
I am of the opinion
that you need to train
across a wide spectrum
of exercise intensities
to optimize both factors.
If you in fact look at
classic training logs
of endurance athletes,
going back to even what we
know about Oscar's training,
they are typically going to
spend something like 70% or so
of their time at a low intensity.
What's that mean exactly?
Mm, depends on the athlete,
but you're probably talking
about something like
between 60 to 80, maybe up to
82% of their heart rate peak.
Most of their time is there.
I'll explain why in a second.
Then, you've got another
additional maybe 20 to 25%
of your time being spent
at a moderate intensity.
Mm, typically something like, again,
82 to 90 or so percent
of your heart rate peak.
And then, three to maybe 6% of the time
at the remaining higher heart rate.
So, this is 92, 93% or so plus.
The reason I'm giving you
kind of rough guidelines there
is every scientific paper
has those zones, if you will,
a little bit differently.
All kinds of different
endurance coaches historically
have set different landmarks and so,
there's no exact numbers there.
And so as a very rough guideline,
I think it is very safe to
assume some split like that
should be highly effective
at improving your VO2 max.
What's that mean in terms of exercises?
Well, actually it's entirely up to you.
VO2 max is, remember,
dependent upon how many
milliliters of oxygen
per kilogram of muscle per minute,
which means the more muscles you utilize,
the higher the VO2 max is.
If you were to go to
get a VO2 max test done,
and let's say you were
not specifically trained
on like a bike,
if you were to get that same
exact test done on a bicycle
versus a treadmill,
where you're running versus cycling,
the score on the treadmill
is going to be about 10% or so
higher than it is on the bike.
And that's simply because
there's a small increase
in the amount of muscles involved
when it comes to running versus cycling.
Now, if you are specifically
trained on the bike
and you cycle a lot,
that may not actually be the case.
And in fact,
highly endurance-trained
folks on, cyclists, rather,
will score higher on a VO2 max test
on the bike than they will on a treadmill.
But that really is now coming down
to test specificity, efficiency,
like all the things that are,
that's not what we're
trying to talk about here.
And so, generally, the
more muscles involved,
the more oxygen being utilized,
the higher that VO2 max.
So when it comes to training,
we want to think about the same thing.
The exercise mode,
I don't want to say it doesn't matter.
It is relevant, but you
have unlimited options.
If you want to bike or swim
or cycle or row, that's great.
If you don't like any of
those traditional modalities
and you want to use something
like an assault bike
or pull a sled, run
uphill, drag something,
those are also incredibly viable options.
It's not the exercise per se
that determines the adaptation,
it's the application
of the exercise, right?
The body works and physiology works
on a principle called the SAID principle,
S-A-I-D,
which stands for specific
adaptation to imposed demand.
So you put a demand on a tissue
to bring in and utilize
oxygen at a high rate,
it will adapt to that specific demand.
So challenging your muscles continuously
to bring in and utilize
oxygen at a rapid rate
is all fundamentally that needs to happen
for you to improve that.
And so again, the mode of the exercise
is not that big of a deal.
If you are new to exercise,
I would generally
recommend you being careful
of exercises that involve
a lot of eccentric action.
So, jumping and landing,
because you're going to get
really sore really fast.
But if not,
feel free to choose
whatever exercise modality
or a combination of them.
Switch it up a little bit,
Do some cycling, do some running
uphill, jump in the pool.
Really up to you.
The intensity in which you do that
is more like what I just explained.
As I apologized at the
beginning of the program,
I, earlier in my life,
grossly underappreciated
the cardiovascular system
as a whole,
and I certainly underappreciated
the importance of low-intensity exercise.
I'll also be candid with you here.
I am not as fond of zone two exercise
as some other folks are.
I certainly don't think it's
bad. It is good for you.
I just don't think you
need to be that worried
about what exact zone you're in.
You want to be something
probably in that lower intensity,
60 to 80-ish percent of your heart rate.
I don't really care where
your millimolars are.
In any of those low intensities,
you're going to be challenging
the ability to bring in
and utilize oxygen over
a long period of time.
Look at any amount of research on that.
It is very clear.
Steady-state, lower-intensity exercise,
especially over time,
six months to a year,
is generally going to improve VO2 max,
probably upwards of five to
10% depending on the person,
the training history and
other contexts like that.
So it's very, very effective
and something I have absolutely
incorporated more and more
into both my life personally
as well as my coaching practice.
So, really important to do that stuff.
On the other end of the equation,
you can do things at an
extremely high intensity
for a short about.
Depending on the study
you want to pull here,
you can see things like
high-intensity intervals.
This could be a combination
of 30 seconds of maximal exercise,
resting 30 seconds,
and repeating that anywhere
between like four and 12 times
can equally improve VO2 max,
if not greater and more so than
your steady-state exercise.
There's a lot more
context that go into that.
It's not necessarily meaning
high intensity is better.
There are some significant
downsides and concerns
with only doing high-intensity exercise,
another thing I've changed my opinion on.
And so, I think we want to
use high-intensity exercise.
There's clear benefit there.
It's fundamentally different, though,
than low-intensity exercise.
So, we're challenging a
different part of the system,
which is why I'm going to argue
you should be incorporating
both most of the time.
It doesn't have to be always
in all of your training,
but you wouldn't want to leave
either one of these things entirely off
if the pure goal here is to maximize VO2.
The reason is,
when you do something
at a higher intensity,
the point of failure in the
tissue becomes different.
So, extending my ability to move
at a lower or moderate intensity
for a long period of time
is challenging different aspects
than it is when I ask it
to introduce a tremendous
amount of fatigue.
So, I'm now into anaerobic metabolism
when I'm going really
hard and really fast.
I can't use oxygen, so I'm
building up a ton of byproducts.
pH is being disturbed,
potential damage is happening,
other things are occurring,
CO2 is getting extremely high.
And so, enhancing my
ability to deal with that
is a similar thing
in terms of increasing
mitochondria biogenesis.
So, more mitochondria,
higher-functioning mitochondria,
larger mitochondria,
increasing aerobic capacity.
All of these same things occur.
And so, again, I don't want
to make the argument that one,
higher intensity or low
intensity is better than another.
I think you should do both.
I will make the same argument
for moderate intensity.
While that isn't as specific and precise
in terms of what it's challenging,
it's reasonable to build some of that
into your equation as well.
Another thing you're going to
find commonly in the research
is a longer about of intervals.
This is described in a
lot of different ways.
A good friend of mine
and an expert in endurance
physiology, Joel Jamieson,
has talked a lot about
high-intensity continuous training,
HICT.
If you're not familiar with that stuff,
I would encourage you to look it up.
It's very, very effective.
Lots of different things and
tools we can pull out here.
One example would be something like,
let's go with a classic runner,
who would do something
more like one mile repeats.
So, run a mile as fast as you can.
This is going to take most folks,
you know, six to eight
or nine minutes or so.
However long it takes
you to run that mile,
rest that same amount of time.
So, it's a one to one work to rest ratio.
So six minutes of running,
six minutes of rest,
and then you repeat that again
for a total of two or three
or perhaps four repetitions.
That's a very long workout
and the average person would
not be able to do that.
But those of you that are not average,
that are good to high
to strong performers listening right now,
that's absolutely within your capabilities
and in fact, you've
probably done it before.
It doesn't have to be that extreme.
You could use shorter durations,
say two minutes, three minutes.
Four minutes is a very, very common one
you'll find in research.
So four minutes of all out exercise,
four minutes of recovery, repeat
it again two to four times.
What's critical to
understand here is these work
when you're actually achieving a maximum
in that time domain.
So, you can't do four minutes at 70%,
rest for four minutes and do that again.
That's going to burn you some calories
and has other benefits of just
making you feel better today
and some other stuff like that.
But in terms of VO2 max,
it's probably not the most
efficient thing you can do.
So to summarize all of that stuff,
spend a good amount of
time at a lower intensity.
That's going to drive efficiency,
a common adaptation there,
since it's going to be the
highest activity you can do
to maximize utilizing fat for fuel.
You're still going to be
burning primarily carbohydrates,
don't get that confused,
but that's the best way to burn some fat.
So, this is typically associated
with higher metabolic efficiency,
getting better at using
fat as a fuel source
and things like that.
It's also easy to recover from.
It's not going to change
your autonomic nervous system that much,
so you typically don't see big drops
in HRV scores.
We don't really see as much over-training
or non-functional overreaching,
elevations in respiratory heart rate,
other signs of hunger or fatigue,
not wanting to train.
Things like that doesn't really happen
when we spend time at lower intensities.
Higher intensities are phenomenal.
Really, really, really time efficient,
but they've got consequences as well.
They're going to be entirely
or mostly anaerobic,
which is okay too
'cause you'll still use the
aerobic side of the equation
to recover from that.
So, super important.
But there's a price to be paid there.
People can run into problems
and you're more likely to see issues
with those metrics I just described.
If you're doing too much
intensity too often,
especially if you're combining this
with a normal stressful life.
So you're doing this kind of exercise,
then you're going right
back into your day job.
You're having difficult meetings,
even if they're exciting
and happy meetings,
you're thinking hard, you're working,
you're getting back to forth,
and you're in a kind of a long,
high-stress environment all day.
Really, really challenging on the system
to be in that high of
a stress at all times.
So other ways you can mitigate that,
we can talk about those
in future episodes.
But just wanted to say,
while high intensity exercise
is very time efficient,
it's not necessarily a free pass either.
Low intensity, not a free pass either.
It's going to leave things on
the table that you're missing.
So to round all that up, again,
I would recommend a
combination of lower intensity,
moderate intensity, and
high intensity training.
The mode of the exercise
in terms of what you choose,
bicycle, kettlebells, circuit training,
it's entirely up to you.
Spin class, whatever you'd like to do.
Frequency can be as high
or as low as you'd like.
There are plenty of studies showing
kind of the higher intensity stuff
done two to three times per
week can improve VO2 max.
But you can also do the lower
intensity stuff every day
or a combination.
So really, you can modify
this based on your lifestyle
and what's going on.
And finally, rest intervals,
they're not incredibly applicable here.
In fact, we've already baked them in.
If you're not doing intervals,
there is no rest interval.
If you are, we typically look
for something like a
one-to-one work to rest ratio.
But you're welcome to do
two to one, one to two,
or any combination of that.
If you train appropriately,
and of course you've got
all the other factors
like your nutrition and sleep
and stress management under control,
it's not unrealistic to
expect a 30 to 50% improvement
in VO2 max after six to 12 months.
You'll find plenty of studies
that land in that ballpark.
The rate of increase obviously goes down
as you become more and more trained.
Now, candidly, you don't have the ability
to improve your VO2 max probably as much
as you do something like your strength,
but you can improve it
significantly nonetheless.
So, you will find plenty of studies
showing even a 10 to 20% increase
in highly-trained
individuals after a year.
In untrained folks,
that probably takes about half that time,
so 10 to 20% improvement in
four to six months or so.
So if you know where you're at right now,
you train appropriately,
fairly consistently,
again, those are reasonable
numbers to expect
after a half a year or so of training.
And as we understand it,
the biggest limiting factor at this point
is probably the time needed
to fill the ventricles back up with blood.
[music]